I would like to start
让我从一个小故事开始。
with the story of Mary,
主人公是玛丽，
a woman from an African village.
一个来自非洲乡村的女人。
Her first memories
在她的记忆里，从小开始
are of her family fleeing violent riots
她全家就在躲避暴乱，颠沛流离，
orchestrated by  the ruling political party.
这一切都拜执政党所赐。
Her brother was murdered by the state-sponsored militia,
她的哥哥被政府支持的民兵杀害，
and she was raped more than once
她也被多次强暴
just because she belonged to the wrong party.
仅仅因为她隶属“不良”党派。
One morning, a month before the election,
选举前一个月的某天早上，
Mary's village was called  to another intimidation meeting.
玛丽所在的村子里上演了一场恐吓拉票集会。
In this meeting, there is a man standing in front of them,
会上，一个男子站在他们面前，
telling them, "We know who you are,
对大家说，“我们认识你们，“
we know who you will vote for,
“知道你们的票会投给谁，”
and if you're not going to drop the right paper,
“如果你们不做出‘正确’的选择，”
we're going to take revenge."
”我们会打击报复。”
But for Mary, this meeting is different.
但对玛丽来说，这个会议不同寻常，
She feels different.
她的感触也不同寻常。
This time, she's waiting for this meeting,
这次，她有所期待，
because this time, she's carrying a small hidden camera in her dress,
因为这次，她衣服里藏了一只隐形摄像机，
a camera that nobody else can see.
一只没人能觉察的摄像机。
Nobody is allowed to film in these meetings.
这些会议严禁摄影，
You risk your life if you do.
否则你将有生命危险。
Mary knows that, but she also knows that the only way to stop them
玛丽明白，但她也知道，只有这样才能阻止他们，
and to protect herself and her community
才能保护她自己以及她的村庄。
is to expose their intimidation,
只有把这种恐吓行为公之于众，
to make sure they understand somebody is following them,
让他们知道有人监督，
to break the impunity they feel.
他们不能无法无天。
Mary and her friends were filming for months, undercover,
玛丽和她的朋友们已经对执政党的恐吓行为
the intimidation of the ruling political party.
秘密地录制了几个月。
(Video) ["Filmed with hidden cameras"]
（偷拍视频）
Man: We are now going to speak about the upcoming elections.
男子：我们要说说接下来的选举。
Nothing can stop us  from doing what we want.
我们势不可挡，
If we hear you are with [The Opposition]
如果你跟“反对党”一伙，
we will not forgive you.
我们绝不原谅。
["Militia intimidation rally"]
（民兵拉票会）
[The Party] can torture you at any time.
“组织”可以随时对你们严刑拷打，
The youth can beat you.
年青人不会放过你。
["Disruption of political meeting"]
（会议被迫中断）
For those who lie, saying they  are back with [The Party],
那些谎称要回归“党”的人，
your time is running out.
你们的日子到头了。
["Party youth militia"]
（青年民兵集会）
Some have died because they rebelled.
有些反抗的人已经丧命，
Some have lost their homes.
有些无家可归。
If you don't work together  with [The Party],
如果不和“党”合作，
you will lead a very bad life.
你们不会有好下场。
Oren Yakobovich: These images were broadcast all over the world,
这些画面现已在世界范围内播出，
but more importantly,
更重要的是，
they have been broadcast back to the community.
也包括当地，
The perpetrators saw them too.
包括施暴者自己也看到了。
They understood somebody is following them.
他们发现有人盯着他们。
They got scared. Impunity was broken.
他们会害怕，不敢再无法无天。
Mary and her friends forced the ruling political party
玛丽和她的朋友们迫使执政党
not to use violence during the election,
在选举中不得使用暴力，
and saved hundreds of lives.
拯救了很多人的生命。
Mary is just one of hundreds of people
玛丽是我们机构里
that my organization had helped  to document human rights violations using cameras.
用相机记录反人权行为的几百人之一。
My background should have led me to a different direction.
我的成长背景本应带我走上一条不同的道路。
I was born in Israel to a right-wing family,
我出生在以色列的一个右翼家庭，
and as long as I remember myself,
自小时候起的印象里，
I wanted to join the Israeli army to serve my country
我一直想要参军报国，
and prove what I believed  was our right for the whole land.
为这片土地伸张正义。
I joined the Israeli army  just after the first intifada,
在第一次巴勒斯坦起义之后，
the first Palestinian uprising,
我加入了以色列军，
and I served in one of the hard-minded,
服役于一个强硬、
toughest, aggressive infantry units,
坚毅、激进的步兵队。
and I got the biggest gun in my platoon.
我也得到队里最大的一架枪。
Quite fast, I became an officer
很快，我当上一名军官,
and got soldiers under my command,
手下也有了几名士兵。
and as time passed, I started serving in the West Bank,
再后来，我开始服役于约旦河西岸，
and I saw these images.
目睹了以下这些画面。
I didn't like what I saw.
我不喜欢眼前的一切。
It took me a while,
挣扎了一段时间后，
but eventually I refused to serve in the West Bank
我最终辞去西岸的职责，
and had to spend time in jail.
这也让我不得已被关入狱。
It was a bit —
其实，
(Applause) —
（掌声）
It was not that bad, I have to say.
其实，我得承认，没那么糟。
It was a bit like being in a hotel, but with very shitty food.
跟旅馆有点像，只是吃的很烂。
(Laughter)
（笑）
In jail, I kept thinking  that I need people to know.
监禁期间，我一直想，我要人们知道，
I need people to understand
我要人们明白，
what the reality in the West Bank looks like.
约旦河西岸的真实面貌。
I need them to hear what I heard,
我要他们听我所听，
I need them to see what I saw,
见我所见，
but I also understood, we need  the Palestinians themselves,
但我也了解，我们需要巴勒斯坦人民，
the people that are suffering,
那些经历苦难的人们，
to be able to tell their own stories,
能讲述他们自己的故事，
not journalists or filmmakers that are coming outside of the situation.
而不是透过置身事外的记者、还是电影制作人。
I joined a human rights organization,
我加入了一个人权机构，
an Israeli human rights  organization called B'Tselem.
一个叫做B'Tselem的以色列组织。
Together, we analyzed the West Bank
我们一同分析了西岸，
and picked 100 families that are living in the most risky places:
挑选出100个身处险境的家庭：
close to checkpoints, near army bases,
它们在关卡旁、在军队基地边、
side by side with settlers.
紧邻着定居点。
We gave them cameras and training.
我们提供相机和相关培训。
Quite fast, we started getting very disturbing images
很快的，我们开始收到一些令人不安的画面：
about how the settlers  and the soldiers are abusing them.
画面里，他们受到士兵和移民者的虐待。
I would like to share with you two clips from this project.
我想和大家分享来自这个项目的两段影片。
Both of them were broadcast in Israel, and it created a massive debate.
两段都在以色列播放过，也引起了巨大的争议。
And I have to warn you,
我得提醒大家，
some of you might  find them quite explicit.
有些人可能会觉得画面过于暴力。
The masked men you  will see in the first clips are Jewish settlers.
第一个画面中的蒙面人是犹太移民者。
Minutes before the camera was turned on,
相机开启的几分钟前，
they approached a Palestinian family
他们朝一个正在耕作的
that was working their land
巴勒斯坦家庭靠近，
and told them that they have to leave the land,
告诉他们必须离开，
because this land belongs to the Jewish settlers.
因为这片地属于他们犹太人定居点。
The Palestinians refused.
巴勒斯坦人拒绝了。
Let's see what happened.
我们看看发生了什么。
The masked men that are approaching are Jewish settlers.
（视频）画面中的蒙面人是犹太移民。
They are approaching the Palestinian family.
他们正向一个巴勒斯坦家庭逼近。
This is a demonstration in the West Bank.
（视频）这是约旦河西岸的一个示威。
The guy in green is Palestinian.
穿绿衣的是巴勒斯坦人。
He will be arrested in a second.
他马上会被逮捕。
Here you see him blindfolded and handcuffed.
现在你可以看到他被戴上眼罩和手铐。
In a few seconds, he regrets  he came to this demonstration.
接下来的几秒钟，他会为自己的到来而后悔。
He's been shot in the foot with a rubber bullet.
他被一个橡胶子弹击中了脚。
He is okay.
他没事儿。
Not all the settlers and the soldiers are acting this way.
并不是所有外来移民和士兵都如此。
We're talking about a tiny minority, but they have to be brought to justice.
我们说的是极小的一部分，但他们必须面对正义的审判。
These clips, and others like them,
这些影片，以及其他类似的，
forced the army and the police to start investigations.
迫使军队和警方开始介入调查。
They've been shown in Israel, of course,
当然，它们已经在以色列播出，
and the Israeli public was exposed to them also.
在以色列的公众面前曝光。
This project redefined the struggle for human rights in the occupied territories,
这个项目重新定义了受统治地区的人权斗争，
and we managed to reduce the number  of violent attacks in the West Bank.
也让西岸暴力袭击的数量得以降低。
The success of this project got me thinking
这个项目的成功让我思考
how I can take the same methodology to other places in the world.
我怎样采取同样的方法，运用到世界其他区域。
Now, we tend to believe that today,
现在，我们愿意相信，
with all of the technology,
在拥有了现有科技、
the smartphones and the Internet,
智能手机和互联网之后，
we are able to see and understand most of what's happening in the world,
我们能够目睹和了解世界上所发生的一切，
and people are able to tell their story —
人们能够讲述他们的故事。
but it's only partly true.
但这只是片面的。
Still today, with all the technology we have,
至今为止，在现有的科技下，
less than half of the world's population has access to the Internet,
世界上只有少于半数的人能使用互联网，
and more than three billion people —
还有超过30亿，
I'm repeating the number —
我重申，
three billion people are consuming news that is censored by those in power.
还有30亿人，
More or less around the same time,
还在审查制度中获取资讯。
I'm approached by a great guy named Uri Fruchtmann.
差不多同时，
He's a filmmaker and an activist.
一个叫Uri Fruchtmann的人找到我。
We understood we were thinking along the same lines,
他是个电影制片人和活动分子。
and we decided to establish Videre, our organization, together.
我们知道我们目标一致，
While building the organization in London,
于是决定共同成立 Videre。
we've been traveling undercover to places
在伦敦组建团队的时候，
where a community  was suffering from abuses, where mass atrocities were happening,
我们秘密走访了一些饱受摧残、暴力横行，
and there was a lack of reporting.
又缺乏曝光的地区。
We tried to understand how we can help.
我们试着了解该如何提供援助。
There were four things that I learned.
我们学到了四点：
The first thing is that we have to engage
首先，我们需要与那些
with communities that are living in rural areas, where violations are happening far from the public eye.
遭受暴力却远离公众视线的偏远村庄建立联系。
We need to partner with them,
我们需要和他们合作，
and we need to understand which images are not making it out there
需要了解那些不为人知的故事，
and help them to document them.
并帮助他们记录下来。
The second thing I learned
其次，我学到
is that we have to enable them  to film in a safe way.
得让他们以一种安全的方式进行拍摄。
Security has to be the priority.
安全第一。
Where I used to work before, in the West Bank,
当我还在西岸工作的时候，
one can take a camera out,
你能掏出摄像机，
most likely not going to get shot,
八成也不会被一枪崩了，
but in places we wanted to work,
但在我们要开展工作的那些地方，
just try to pull a phone out, and you're dead — literally dead.
要敢拿出手机你就死定了，真的死定了。
This is why we decided
这就是为什么我决定
to take the operation undercover when necessary, and use mostly hidden cameras.
在必要的时候，尽可能地使用隐形相机进行拍摄。
Unfortunately, I can't show you the hidden cameras we're using today — for obvious reasons —
很不幸，我不能给大家展示我们正在使用的偷拍相机，
but these are cameras we used before.
但这些是我们曾经用使过的机型。
You can buy them off the shelf.
你可以在店里买到的。
Today, we're building  a custom-made hidden camera,
如今，我们定制了一款隐形相机，
like the one that Mary was wearing
类似玛丽身上的
in her dress to film the intimidation meeting of the ruling political party.
记录执政党恐吓胁迫行径的相机。
It's a camera that nobody can see,
这款相机很隐蔽
that blends into the environment, into the surroundings.
可以很好地融入周遭环境。
Now, filming securities go beyond using hidden cameras.
现在，拍摄安全比使用隐形相机本身更重要。
Being secure starts way before the activist is turning the camera on.
在打开摄像机之前，就得确保安全。
To keep our partners safe,
为了保障我们合作伙伴的安危，
we work to understand the risk of every location
我们致力了解每个地方、
and of every shot before it's happened,
拍摄每张照片的风险，
building a backup plan if something goes wrong,
在可能出错的环节做好应急措施，
and making sure  we have everything in place before our operations start.
在展开行动之前，确保一切就绪。
The third thing I learned is the importance of verification.
第三，我学到核实的重要性。
You can have an amazing shot of atrocity,
你能捕捉到惊心动魄的暴行，
but if you can't verify it, it's worth nothing.
但如果无法核实真伪，那它没有任何意义。
Recently, like in the ongoing war  in Syria or the war in Gaza,
近来，在叙利亚，又或者加沙持续的战争中，
we've seen images that are staged  or brought from a different conflict.
我们看到一些摆拍的，或从其他冲突中挪用的影像。
This misinformation destroyed the credibility of the source,
这些不实信息不光损害了消息来源的可信度，
and it's harmed the credibility of other reliable and trustworthy sources.
也影响了其他原本可信可靠的消息源。
We use a variety of ways to make sure we can verify the information
我们用多种途径确保消息能够核实，
and we can trust the material.
素材值得信任。
It starts with vetting the partners,
这都从我们对合作者的审核开始，
understanding who they are, and working with them very intensively.
认识他们，和他们紧密合作。
How do you film a location?
你该如何拍摄一个场景呢？
You film road signs, you film watches, you film newspapers.
你可以拍拍路标，手表，报纸，
We are checking maps, looking at maps, double-checking the information,
我们可以查看地图，核对信息，
and looking also at  the metadata of the material.
查询后备资料。
Now, the fourth and the most important thing I learned
第四点，也是我学到的最多的
is how you use images  to create a positive change.
是如何利用这些图像来创造一些正面的改观。
To have an effect,
为了达到效应，
the key thing is how you use the material.
关键在于如何使用这些材料。
Today, we're working with hundreds of activists filming undercover.
今天，我们同几百名积极分子一起秘密拍摄。
We work with them both to understand  the situation on the ground
我们一起了解当下处境，
and which images  are missing to describe it,
看看还缺少哪些画面，
who are the ones that are  influencing the situation,
谁能改变局面，
and when to release the material to advance the struggle.
什么时候发布这些资料，来推进斗争。
Sometimes, it's about putting it in the media,
有时，这事关媒体，
mostly local ones, to create awareness.
主要是当地的媒体，来提高人们的意识。
Sometimes it's working with decision makers,
有时，这事关决策者，
to change laws.
要他们去完善法制。
Sometimes, it's working with lawyers to use as evidence in court.
有时，是把这些资料当做证据。
But more than often,
但更多时候，
the most effective way to create a social change
引发社会变革最有效的方法，
is to work within the community.
是从体制内部开展工作。
I want to give you one example.
给大家举个例子。
Fatuma is part of a network of women that are fighting abuses in Kenya.
Fatuma是肯尼亚一个妇女反暴力组织中的一员，
Women in her community have been harassed constantly on their way to school and on their way to work.
社区中的女性时常在上学和工作途中遭遇骚扰。
They are trying to change  the behavior of the community from inside.
她们试图由内而外地改变这种局面。
In the next clip,
在接下来的影片中，
Fatuma is taking us with her on her journey to work.
Fatuma将带领我们走上她上班的路途。
Her voice is superimposed on images that she filmed herself
她为这段偷拍的影片
using hidden cameras.
做了旁白。
(Video) Fatuma Chiusiku:  My name is Fatuma Chiusiku.
（视频）我叫Fatuma Chiusiku，
I'm 32 years old, a mother,
32岁，是一个母亲，
And Ziwa La Ng'Ombe is my home.
家在Ziwa La Ng'Ombe。
Each morning, I ride the mini-bus
每天早上，我乘坐小巴，
Number 11.
11路。
But instead of a peaceful journey to work,
但上班的车程并非一路安宁，
each day begins with fear.
而是充满恐惧。
Come with me now
跟着我，
and use my eyes
用我的眼睛，
to feel what I feel.
体会我的感受。
As I walk, I think to myself:
我边走边想：
Will I be touched?
我会再一次被售票员偷摸吗？
Grabbed?
偷抓？
Violated by this conductor again?
冒犯？
Even the men inside
就连车里的男人们
the way they look at me
他们看我的样子，
touch my body, rub against me,
摸着我的身子，磨蹭我，
grab me,
抓我，
and now, as I sit in my seat
现在，当我坐在座位上，
I only wish my mind was full of thoughts for my day,
多希望每天心里惦记着的只是我的生活，
my dreams, my children at school,
我的梦想，我在上学的孩子，
but instead I worry about the moment when we will arrive
但我却要担心公车何时抵达，
and I will be violated again.
而我是否会再一次被侵犯。
OY: Today, there is a new front in the fight for human rights.
今天，我们的人权斗争已经到了全新的阶段。
I used to carry a big gun.
我曾经手持重型枪械。
Now, I am carrying this.
现在，我拿着这个。（偷拍相机）
This is a much more powerful and much, much more effective weapon.
这是个更有力，更有效的武器。
But we have to use its power wisely.
但我们要善用它，
By putting the right images in the right hands at the right time,
在对的时间，用对的影像，给对的人。
we can truly create an impact.
只有这样，我们才能真的影响世界。
Thank you.
谢谢。
(Applause)
（掌声）
Thank you.
谢谢大家。
(Applause)
（掌声）